Inventory of the W. G. Kubick papers
Hoover Institution Archives
W. G. Kubick papers
1940-2000
2000C81
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, testimony, photocopies of United States government documents, and printed matter relating to the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II and to subsequent proposals for reparations payments.
Kubick, W. G.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical and Historical Note
William G. Kubick was born in Chicago, Illinois and moved with his family to California in 1922, when he was eight. In 1942, Kubick joined the United States Army and participated in landings throughout the Pacific. He was among the first United States occupation forces who participated in assault landings on Japan.
In 1981, Kubick testified before the Seattle hearing of the Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians (CWRIC) as a veteran of World War II. Kubick became known as an opponent of reparations payments to Japanese Americans interned during World War II and continued to voice his support for President Roosevelt's Executive Order 9066 in 2000.
Scope and Content of Collection
The W.G. Kubick papers consist of materials created and compiled by Kubick on the topic of the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II in preparation for Senate hearings in Seattle in 1981 on the Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians. These materials include writings, correspondence, testimony, photographs, printed matter, and photocopies of United States government documents from agencies such as the Federal Bureau of Investigation.
The collection also documents Kubick's later involvement in writing about reparations and appearing on broadcast shows. These materials include documentation of Kubick's television and radio appearances, as well as articles and letters to the editor in support of the United States' relocation of Japanese Americans to internment camps. Senate Bill S. 2116 and House Bill H.B. 442, regarding civil liberties violations and reparations, are also included in the collection.
Kubick's original order has been maintained.
Related Collections
Lillian Baker papers, Hoover Institution Archives.
David D. Lowman papers, Hoover Institution Archives.
Compensation (Law) -- United States.; Japanese Americans -- Civil rights.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; Japanese Americans.; World War, 1939-1945--Reparations.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Japanese evacuation materials, 1943-1983 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Printed matter, including:
  United States Senate, Ninety-Eighth Congress, First Session. Japanese American Redress: Hearing Before the Subcommittee on Administrative Practice and Procedure of the Committee on the Judiciary on S. 1520, the World War II Civil Liberties Violations Redress Act, and Reports of the Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1984.
  United States War Department. Japanese Evacuation from the West Coast 1942 - Final Report. Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1943.
- Relocation and internment materials, 1940-2000
  Contains works compiled in three volumes, based on categories and topics devised by Kubick.
  - Volume I, 1942-1988
    - Government documents and reports, 1942-1981 (Box-folder 1: 2)
      Includes executive orders, reports from the United States Justice Department, and lists of names on Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) files, along with correspondence and clippings. Also includes witness testimony from Kubik in support of President Roosevelt's Executive Order 9066.
    - Correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      Includes general correspondence, letters to editors, and correspondence with Congress, Lilian Baker, and David D. Lowman.
  - Volume II, 1940-1990
    - David D. Lowman typescript, school board reparations, and Hiroshima, 1982-1985 (Box 1: 4)
      Information about Seattle school board reparations and the United States bombing of Hiroshima, Japan. Includes David D. Lowman's typescript, "Magic and the Japanese Relocation and Internment."
    - Writings, 1940-1990 (Box-folder 1: 5)
      Includes Kubick's articles and correspondence.
  - Volume III, 1971-2000
    - Lillian Baker correspondence, Trask Report, and Gordon Hirabayashi, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 2: 1)
      The Trask Report is the written statement of Dr. David F. Trask, Chief Historian of the U.S. Army Center for Military History, Department of the Army, before the Subcommittee on Administrative Law and Government Relations of the House Committee on the Judiciary, Second Session, 98th Congress: War Relocations and Internment of Civilians, June 20, 1984 (copy).
    - Veterans' actions, writings, and historical landmarks, 1971-2000 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      Includes correspondence from the Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States (VFW) regarding VFW Resolution 442 and the American Legion resolution supporting H.R. 1334. Also includes materials on Manzanar (California Registered Historical Landmark Number 850) and Tule Lake (850-2).